[Treehouse]
In the last video, we saw how to create some very basic objects
but now we're going to be adding functions to our objects
to create something called a method.
So we've seen how encode keys and values into our objects,
but here's a cool thing that we can do.
Let's say we want to not only just have not only a regular value
but remember, values are functions just like any other.
So what if we wanted to assign to the value
greet
the function
We'll take no parameters.
and the body will be something like this:
console.log
Hello
I am Jim
So what can we do with that?
Well, let's go ahead, and let's comment out
all of this code right here, since we don't need it,
and what we can do is, we can say
Jim.greet
and remember, this is just a function,
so we could execute it by adding
parentheses after Jim.greet
So what we should see here,
if we refresh,
is hello, I am Jim.
Now there's nothing particularly interesting about that.
I mean, yeah, we added a function into our object,
and in fact, we've seen that a lot.
In fact, everytime we type console.log,
we see the exact same thing.
Console is an object that has a key
of log that happens to be a function,
which we execute with parentheses.
So that's what's been going on with console.log
and a few of the other methods that we've seen.
We use method to describe a function
that is a property of an object.
So if we just had the function called greet,
we'd generally refer to that as a function;
however, since the function greet right now
is associated with the object Jim,
we refer to it as a method on the object Jim,
because it's a function associated with specific object.
Now, we'll see a little bit more about how
methods can differ slightly from functions,
but let's just take a look at what we have now.
We have a basic function that just says
Hello, I am Jim.
However, you'll notice that there is some repeated information here.
The name Jim is also part of the key name.
So if we said Jim.name is James,
what would happen?
We would still get Hello, I am Jim,
but if we take a look at Jim.name,
it's James.
So if we type Jim.greet,
the information isn't quite up to date.
Ideally, when we say Hello, I am,
we should read the name property of this person.
So how could we do that?
Well, let's take a look at 1 way we can do this.
We could say hello, I am
leave a space there
and then use + to concatenate another string,
and we want to get this right here,
Jim.name
So we can type in Jim.name
and if we refresh, we can see it says
Hello, I am James, because it's now reading
Jim.name
which we we changed in the code on line 17
to be the value James.
And if we change it back to Jim by doing
Jim.name=Jim
and then we type Jim.greet
to call that method once again,
we'll see it now says Hello, I am Jim.
Now this kind of works;
however, if we, for instance,
wanted to create another object representing another person--
let's say we create Nick,
and I'm going to remove some of these extra things that we don't need.
Let's just change the name to Nick,
and then what do we have to do?
Well, if we had just left it like that,
if we did Nick.greet,
it says Hello, I am James.
What what we would have to do there is
change it to say Nick,
and it gets to be too much to handle.
Even though they're the same methods,
really all we want to have changed is
what's in here.
So ideally, we wouldn't have 2 different methods;
we'd have the same method, but it would be
relative to the person we're talking about,
or it would have context as to what object
we are referring to.
So 1 way we can think about maybe
abstracting this a little more is
instead of greet taking no parameters,
we could say it takes a parameter called person.
Instead of saying Jim.name,
we'll say person.name
and I'll just copy this function between the 2 of them.
Again, we don't want to copy and paste our code,
but we'll see how JavaScript allows us to
get the same effect without doing this ugly code right here.
So I'll just re-indent that.
So the greet functions between Jim and Nick
are the same,
so if we refresh,
it looks like we have an error here,
and that's because it cannot read
property name of undefined,
because we've changed how greet works,
so we can't just say Jim.greet and pass at nothing.
We have to give it the context of the person we want to use.
In this case, we'll say Jim.greet and we'll pass ourselves in
or Jim as the object.
So if you refresh, it says now
Hello, my name is James.
We can do the same thing for Nick.greet
and we'll pass at the context, which is Nick,
And we can see we get Hello, I am Nick
and Hello, I am James.
But again, this isn't ideal.
Obviously, this seems pretty stupid
when we do Jim.greet and pass Jim
or Nick.greet and pass Nick.
We're duplicating our information on the line
when really, there should be a way to
get the context of the object of the
method being called.
For instance, if we're calling Jim.greet,
we should know that this greet method
is referring to the object, Jim
without having to explicitly pass it in.
Similarly, when we say Nick.greet,
the greet method should know that we're
operating on the object, Nick
without having to explicitly pass that context in, as well.
Well, fortunately JavaScript provides us a
special sort of variable,
though it's not really a variable,
but it acts a lot like one,
and it's called this,
and that's this, THIS.
It's a little bit confusing to talk about,
but I'll try to put some emphasis when I'm
referring to the this object in JavaScript.
So why don't we try a new approach?
Instead of saying person
and passing it in to greet,
we'll use this thing called &quot;this&quot; in its place.
You'll notice our editor has highlighted this
with a special color,
because it has a special meaning in JavaScript.
Now I'm gonna do the same thing for Nick,
so we can just see that we have
the same object between the 2 of them.
I will change our code here.
Instead of passing in our context,
we use this to give us the context
of how our methods were called.
Even though these are 2 different methods,
they could be the same.
For instance, we could do this,
so we don't duplicate our code.
You'll notice I'm not calling greet,
so I'm saying Nick's greet
is the same as Jim's greet.
So if we run this,
I refreshed it, and we get the same code.
The greet functions between the 2 of them
are exactly the same.
However, when they are invoked,
they're invoked with 2 different contexts.
When we call it Jim.greet,
this holds the value of Jim.
However, when we call it Nick.greet,
this holds the value of Nick.
And this is always going to be bound to the
value at the very last second.
Normally, our variables are easy to reason about
because we can look at our variable scope
in our actual code and reason fairly easily
about what any variable will bind to.
However, this is very special
in that its actually given its value when we call our method
instead of when we write our method.
So how does this get its binding?
Or how does this get its context?
Well, its all in how we call our method.
For instance, if we call it Jim.greet,
because we called it like a method using
this dot notation.
When we call greet, it's called with this
bound to what's on the left-hand side
of our dot here,
which is Jim.
The same thing happens for Nick.
When we call Nick.greet,
JavaScript sees that we're calling the method on an object Nick,
and it will assign this to the value of Nick.
So if we refresh, we can see it still works
and this binding works with the square bracket notation, as well.
If we say Jim, with the open square bracket, greet
and then we're calling the method,
so we have close square brackets and then our parentheses
the effect will be exactly the same.
Now there is a gotcha here.
So this works, because we're calling
Jim &quot;greet&quot; then parentheses here.
What what happens if we try to take our
greet method and store it into a variable?
With a var Jim greet = Jim.greet
and we're not putting parentheses.
We're trying to actually get a reference to our function,
so Jim.greet will now contain a function.
But what happens when we try to
call JimGreet like that?
What will happen?
If we refresh, we'll see it says Hello I am.
And that's because, when we call JimGreet
here on line 29,
we're calling it as a normal function
not as a property of Jim.
So this binding of this to the object
only happens when we call it like Nick.greet
or using square brackets Jim open square brackets greet
and call it immediately.
If we grab that function out of the object
and store it into a variable and call it later,
we've lost the context to what that method was referring to,
and it just becomes a normal function.
But what happened, we just see, Hello, I am
and that's actually interesting, because
what is this when we call a normal function
that is not being invoked like a method?
Let's just check it out.
We'll create a function called what is this?
It will simply console.log the value of this,
so our last line here in our console.log
we'll call what is this
and our last line when we see it here
is we see logged something called DOM window.
Now this is a very problematic part of JavaScript here.
When we call a function without a method binding,
like Jim.greet, we just call it.
This refers to the global object.
What's the global object?
Well, in our case, inside the browser,
it's window,
which means anytime we create a variable,
it actually is created as property of
this global object.
For instance, windw is just an object;
however, any of our global variables,
like, for instance, in this script, we've defined a variable called Jim,
it's assigned as a property of the window object.
So to reach the variable Jim,
we can just type window.Jim
and we see we see we get the object which
represents Jim.
So what happened is when we call
what is this,
this is literally window.
And the reason we got an empty string
after I am
is because window in the browser actually has a name property,
and by default,
it's the empty string.
So what if we change window.name
or what if we just said var name = the window?
So by doing that,
window.name is the window,
and if we call it Jim Greet again,
since we're calling it like a function, this
will be bound to window and window.name
is the window.
So this is actually a very dangerous part.
If we call our method in the incorrect way
and use this,
we could end up reading from or signing to
the global name space,
which can really difficult to debug
and really harmful to our programs.
In fact, in later versions of JavaScript
that are being developed now and even in some browsers
in strict mode, when we call a function,
like this, what is this?
without any context,
this will be undefined.
However, the default behavior is that this will be the window,
which can be problematic.
So be careful.
Whenever you see this in a function,
recognize that it's to be used as a method,
meaning that it should only be called
in a way where this will be bound to an object that you're referring to.
Actually, we can assign the the value of this
when we envoke it ourselves,
and we'll be doing that in the next video.
In the next video, we'll see how to control
the value of this with the call and apply methods.
[Treehouse]