[Treehouse]
In JavaScript, objects are the foundations
for almost every type that we use.
In this video, we'll learn how to create basic JavaScript objects for our programs.
So now we'll be learning about 1 of the most
core and foundational pieces of JavaScript,
the object.
Objects can be very simple to begin with,
but there's very interesting and complex
parts when we start wanting to do more
advanced things with our objects.
In this video, we'll be working on a very basic HTML page
much like our previous pages that we used
to learn arrays and other types.
It's a simple HTML page
that includes 1 JavaScript file called objects.js
and this is where we'll be experimenting
and learning about objects.
So what is an object?
In JavaScript, an object is simply
a datatype that associates keys and values.
Much like how the JavaScript array stores
multiple values by numeric key or index,
a JavaScript object can store many values
by a key that is described by a string.
So let me show you what that looks like.
I'm going to create an object that
represents me, or Jim.
So I'm going to create a normal variable
and I'm going to name this variable Jim,
and the way we create an object or an object literal
is with curly braces.
Now inside of these curly braces,
what we are going to define are the
keys and values of our object.
Remember that arrays were ordered so we
didn't have to give it the keys,
but because the key of the object could be anything,
we have to specify our keys next to our values.
So let's assign some keys and values to Jim.
One key would be name,
and the way we
differentiate keys and values is
first, we give the key,
then we have a colon,
and then the value comes after that,
and our value for name would be Jim.
Now this is a very basic object.
It only has 1 key and value pair.
You can see that on the left-hand side of the colon,
name specifies the key,
and on the right-hand side
is the value for that key.
So the way that we can access that is
for instance, we could do Jim.name
Now let's see what's inside of this.
We can do console.log
and pass at jim.name
So if we save this and we refresh,
we can see that it logged Jim to the console,
because Jim.name is Jim,
and we can play with our object interactively.
For instance, if we do Jim.name,
we can see it's a string Jim.
Additionally, we can assign values to our keys
by doing Jim.name equals
and maybe a different value, like James.
So now if we inspect Jim.name,
we can see that it stores the new string, James.
So these keys and values are much like variables
except they're associated with an object.
Now we can add multiple key and value pairs to our object
by separating them with a comma.
If we wanted to add some more information,
like skills,
we could put a comma, our next key, a colon, and then our next value.
The values don't have to be strings.
They can be any type that we can store in a variable;
for instance, an array.
So we can say, for instance, my skills are
JavaScript and let's say Ruby
and dancing.
I'm an excellent dancer.
So if we save this out,
and we were to come back and we can
inspect our object again by, let's say,
typing Jim.skills,
and we can see we get the array of my skills back,
and we can modify this array just like any other object.
We could reassign skills to a different set of objects or even a string.
But this is the simple way we read values from our object.
Similarly, we can write values into our keys
by simply doing Jim.skills equals everything.
So that's the basics of objects.
It's very simple; it's just a series of
keys and values that we can assign to and read from.
Let's take a look our object literal again.
Our line is getting pretty long.
It looks like we're reaching the
right-hand side of our screen,
so it's a little bit difficult to read.
So let's take a look at the way we would
normally indent or format object literals.
Usually, what we can do is,
after we have our opening curly brace,
we can add a new line and indent it.
Right now, my indentation is about 4 spaces
but depending on your indentation, it may go further or less far.
And usually what we do is
break up each key and value pair onto a different line.
Finally, we'll have the closing curly brace
for our object literal
on another line out-dented to the original level of indentation.
This makes it very easy to see where the
beginning of our Jim object definition begins and ends.
Now there's another interesting thing we can do here.
Well see that our keys right now are strings,
and they are surrounded by quotation marks.
This is not strictly necessary with the keys
that we're using here,
because if we use a key that is a valid identifier,
that is, it would be acceptable to use as a variable name
or as a function name,
then we don't have to surround the key in our literal with quotes.
So basically, anything that's a valid variable name could be written like this.
And this is just a shorthand that makes a little bit easier to parse and modify our code.
Again, you're always safe quoting your key strings,
but in these cases, usually we have identifiers for our keys that
don't need quotation marks,
so we'll just skip it.
We can see by loading the page, it behaves the exact same way.
So we put in Jim.name and get back Jim.
And we can do skills and everything works just fine.
Now we've seen that we can use this dot notation.
Jim.name
which basically means from the object Jim,
we're going to retrieve the key name,
and this works for the identifiers that we've given it.
However, what happens if we have a key that is,
for instance, favorite color.
And I'm just talking favorite color with a space.
Well, since there's a space in our key,
we have to wrap it in quotation marks,
and we can give our key a name.
We'll save favorite color.
Now this isn't a great key name;
however, we can use it,
because any string can be used as our key.
And we'll say the value is green.
You'll notice I added another comma after skills
before adding in our next key value pair,
and this is necessary.
So, we can refresh,
and we'll see if that's fine.
However, how do we access that?
We can't do something like this.
Jim.favorite color
As you can imagine, that's not going to work in the JavaScript processor.
If we refresh, we'll actually get a syntax error,
because we can't just have a space here.
It doesn't really know what to do with it.
Fortunately, we have an alternate way of
specifying the key that we want to retrieve
or set on our object,
and it will look familiar,
because it's the way we access values in our arrays.
We use a square bracket around our key,
and then of course, we have to wrap our key in a string.
We'll just do console.log
and we can refresh,
and we can see we can now access green.
Now in fact, we can do that all the way around.
We can even do it with name;
again, it has to be quoted if it's inside of the square brackets.
So you'll see, it's exactly the same,
and we can even assign to it by doing
jim
the key, favorite color
equals blue.
So now before we actually log our favorite color,
we'll have have changed it from green to blue.
We should see blue output in the console.
So that's the very basics of it.
We can access our keys by either using the
dot notation or the square bracket notation
with a expression inside;
for instance, our string that represents our key,
and when we define our object literals,
we can use any string key,
and if that key happens to be a valid identifier,
we can actually omit the quotation marks
to make it a little bit easier to read.
So now we've seen how to create basic objects.
In the next video, we'll be adding functions to our objects
to create something called methods.
[Treehouse]