[Treehouse]
So far we've seen how to create strings using string literals.
Now we'll see how to create strings by joining other strings together.
The first common thing that you'll do with strings
is concatenate them with other strings. That means to join them together.
For instance, if we had a variable called &quot;part1,&quot;
and the string was &quot;Hello&quot; with a space after it.
Then if we add another variable called &quot;part2&quot; with a value &quot;World!&quot;,
we could create another string that is the joining of these two by using the plus operator.
We'll store this into a variable called &quot;whole,&quot;
which will be part1 plus part2.
We can do console.log(whole), save it, and refresh it,
and we can see now &quot;whole&quot; contains the string &quot;Hello World!&quot;
You can concatenate string literals themselves instead of just variables.
For instance, if we replaced part1 with &quot;Hello&quot; and part2 with the literal string &quot;World!&quot;
the same effect will happen where whole is &quot;Hello World!&quot;
We can save and refresh our browser and see that it is the same.
I'm going to change it back to being our variables here.
Now we can concatenate anywhere that we have a string.
For instance, if we wanted to add on to whole here, you do whole +
and we'll add some extra exclamation points.
If we refresh, we'll see that the string is now concatenated.
We can use it as as many plus operators to concatenate as many strings together
as we would like.
Now we can use the concatenation operator also to make our code a little easier to read.
For instance, let's take a look at our multi-line string.
Here by reading it, we can see that there are two new line characters, which make it a 3-line string.
However, the literal in our code is all done in one line.
Ideally, it would be nice if we could split it onto multiple lines,
but we remember that we cannot split a literal string onto multiple lines in JavaScript,
but we can, however, create multiple strings, place them on different lines,
and concatenate them together with the plus operate.
For instance, we can do something like this.
We'll end our first string right after our new line character by adding a double quote.
Then we'll use the plus operator to say we're going to concatenate another string onto this string.
We'll add another quotation mark, another plus to concatenate,
and we'll create the last string by adding another quote.
Now this in itself should not have changed the value of our multi-line string.
We can find out by saving it and refreshing in our browser,
and we still see this is line 1, this is line 2, and this tab is line 3,
but that advantage we now have is we're actually able to split this onto multiple lines.
For instance, we we could do a new line right after the plus
and we can arrange it however we like.
We have to remember to have the plus on the end of the line.
This is because when JavaScript sees a plus, it knows that there
should be something on the right-hand side.
It'll search for the second operand by doing down to the next line where it finds line two
and again finds like 3 for the final concatenation.
If we save this out and we refresh our browser, we see that the result is the same.
Now, it may not be the prettiest way to create a multi-line string,
but in JavaScript it's pretty much our only option.
We can either have all of our string on a single string literal on one line,
or we can split it into multiple substrings and add our new lines by using \n
and concatenating them together using the plus operator.
Up next, we'll learn about some of the properties and methods of strings.
[Treehouse]