[Treehouse]
In the last video, we saw how to create strings and learned about the escape characters for quotes.
No we'll see some other escape characters that we can use in JavaScript strings.
For instance, the backslash itself needs to be escaped,
because the backslash special meaning is itself escaping.
For instance, if we have something like a path on a Windows computer,
the path uses backslashes to delimit the folders in its path.
You might have something like c:\folder\myfile.txt.
Let's do a console.log with our path.
If we refresh our page, if we look at our string, we see it's not what we wanted.
It's c:oldermyfile.txt, which is not what we wanted. What can we do?
Let's go back to our JavaScript file, and we can actually see that TextMate is
highlighting the backslash and f and the backslash and m.
That's because the backslash and the next character defined what character
we're escaping inside of our strings.
If we actually look back in our output from our browser,
we'll notice not only are the backslashes missing, but the f is missing from &quot;folder.&quot;
That's because backslash f has a special meaning inside of a string.
There are only a few backslash escape characters
that we really need to worry about, but right now
lets just focus on getting our backslashes into our string.
To add a literal backslash into a string in JavaScript
all we need to do is do backslash backslash.
Though it appears there are two backslashes in our string,
it'll only be displayed as one when we actually use our string.
We'll do the same thing for our other backslash by adding another backslash.
Now if we save out our strings.js and return to our browser and refresh,
we'll see that the string now contains the characters that we want,
including our backslashes and that missing backslash f.
Now what if we want to create a string with multiple lines.
Well, let's try to do that. We'll create a variable called &quot;multiline,&quot;
and we want our string to say &quot;This is line 1&quot;
then &quot;This is line 2&quot; and finally &quot;This is line 3.&quot;
We might expect this to work and create a string with 3 lines in it,
but if we save it out and refresh, we get another syntax error.
That is because we cannot create a string that spans multiple lines in JavaScript.
The closing quotation mark must come on the same line
as the opening quotation mark for it to be a valid string.
So if we try to smash all these together and save it out, and we refresh, it will work.
Let's do a console.log to see what the actual result is.
We can refresh and see that we get a string that's all on one line.
We can make the string multiple lines by using another special character.
In order to create multiple lines inside of our string,
the character we're going to use is called a &quot;new line character.&quot;
All we do to use this is figure out where we want our line to break.
For instance, our first line will break right after the character &quot;1&quot; and before &quot;This.&quot;
We insert our character by doing backslash n.
If we save this out, and we refresh it, we'll see now our string contains two lines.
We can easily make this 3 lines by just including another special
new line character where we want our line to break.
If we save this out and refresh, we now have a 3-line string exactly like we wanted it.
Now there is one more special character that we use fairly regularly,
and it's the &quot;tab&quot; character.
This is the character that would normally be
inserted when you hit the &quot;tab&quot; key on your keyboard.
To insert a tab, all we do is backslash t,
and a new tab character will be inserted into our string in its place.
If we refresh, we can see now a tab character
appears between &quot;this&quot; and &quot;is&quot; on the third line of our string.
Now you've seen how to create strings in JavaScript.
In the next video, we'll see how to joint strings together to create new strings.
[Treehouse]