[music]
Variables are what allow us to store and retrieve data in our programs.
They're very easy to use, but there are some very specific rules
that we need to use in our JavaScript programs.
In Netcom videos, we'll learn how to use variables in JavaScript.
Setting variables is easy to do in JavaScript.
Since JavaScript is dynamically typed,
when we create a variable all we have to do is give it a name and any value.
In other languages that are instead statically typed,
each variable  must have a specific type associated with it.
For instance, a variable could be just a number,
just a string or just some other type.
But we don't have to worry about giving a type to a variable in JavaScript.
We can create a variable and assign its value to a number
and then later, to a string; it doesn't really matter.
Variables can hold any type, at any time.
Right here, I have a basic HTML page and JavaScript setup.
In the HTML page, I have just some basic HTML
and I include my script with this &lt;script&gt; tag.
The \&quot;myscript.js\&quot; right now is empty,
except for a simple comment here.
But this is where we'll be experimenting with variables.
So let's dive in!
In Intro to Programming, we saw how to set variables like this:
var color = \&quot;red\&quot;;
This statement is made out of 4 parts.
The first is the var keyword.
This says that we're declaring a variable.
Right after the var keyword is the name of our variable.
Now this can be almost any type of word.
We'll see the rules  for the names of our variables a little bit later.
Then we have the equals sign,
which says we're initializing a value
or setting an initial value.
Finally, we have the value we're going to set to the variable.
This can be any type--
like a string, a number, an array;
or it can be an expression, like a mathematical expression,
the concatenation of strings
or the result of a function call--
or really any other expression.
Now we've sort of taken a look at what variables
can  be used for in Intro To Programming.
But let me give you a concrete example
of where we might want to use a variable
when we're programming JavaScript in the browser.
In my index.html page
I have a div with the ID of \&quot;myDiv\&quot;.
Now using JavaScript and some built-in functions in the browser,
we can manipulate things, like its color and its background color.
So let's take a look at how we might do that with JavaScript.
So if I use this expression right here,
this will take the element with the ID of \&quot;myDiv\&quot;
and set its background color to black.
Now, the specifics of the methods and functions called here
are not important and not what we're going to focus on.
But I'll give you a little overview.
Document is a variable that's built into our Web page.
It's always available and it represents our page.
On that, we call a method called getElementById--
and what this will do is return the div
with the ID of ('myDiv').
Then on myDiv there's an object named \&quot;style\&quot; with a property, \&quot;background\&quot;--
and we can either read from that to get the current background color
of that element or we can set to it, to set its color.
So if I save this out and we take a look at our page,
this is the div that we are focusing on.
If we Refresh the page, we'll see that nothing happens--
and that's because the way our script is included right now,
it's run before our page is set up.
Now, the easiest way to fix this is to take the &lt;script&gt; tag
and put it at the end of our body.
This means by the time our &lt;script&gt; tag is included into the page,
our div, for instance, has already been put into the page and is accessible;
whereas before, it was not.
There are other methods we could employ to fix this problem,
but this one's good because it lets the entire page load in
before we do any JavaScript interaction,
which allows our page to load a little bit faster.
So now if we Refresh the page,
we should see our div now has the background color, black.
Now that's all right--but if we go to \&quot;myscript.js\&quot; and let's say, for instance,
we want to change the text color to white--
well, what could we do?
We could do a similar line,
and instead of setting \&quot;style.background\&quot; we could do \&quot;style.color\&quot;--
which, in this case, is how we set the CSS text color of a div.
Now if we did this, this would work.
And we can see, now are text color is white.
But this isn't a very good way to code.
We have a lot of repeated code here.
For instance, we get the \&quot;ElementById\&quot; twice,
even though it's the same element.
Instead, we could use a variable,
and we'll call it \&quot;myDiv\&quot;.
We're giving it a descriptive name--in this case,
we're giving it the name of the id  that's already associated with the div,
but it doesn't have to be the same.
For instance, I could say \&quot;myContainer\&quot; or anything else.
But to be clear, I'll do \&quot;myDiv\&quot;.
Now I can use the equals sign to assign a value.
And the value that I want to assign is the actual div.
Now, in this expression, the div
is represented by all of this, right here--
document.getElementById, passing at ('myDiv').
This evaluates to the div that we actually want.
So I can take that out, and now our myDiv variable
contains that div and we can use it over and over again.
So instead of using the document.getElementById
over and over again, we can instead
use the variable that we set--for instance, myDiv.
And we can do it again, here.
So anytime we want to get or set something on myDiv,
we simply use the value stored in the myDiv variable.
This allows us to easily change our code.
For instance, if we change the actual ID
of the element that we want to use.
Instead, now we'd only have to change this in 1 place--
right here, where we set the variable--
and myDiv and the rest of the code would reflect that change.
So let's save this out and see if it works.
If we Refresh, we can see the same behavior is taking place.
The div now has a black background with white text.
[?Jazzy music]
Now you should have a very basic understanding
of how variables work in JavaScript.
In the next video, we'll see the rules that JavaScript has
for our variable names.
[Treehouse]