[? Music ?] [Treehouse]
So far we've seen  how to use 2 features of functions,
arguments and return values.
Now we'll learn about how scope works in functions.
We've seen a basic example of creating a function that takes arguments,
performs some actions, and returns a value.
Now, there's another property of functions that's very important
in JavaScript to understand, and that's called &quot;scope.&quot;
Let's take a look at a very simple example.
Let's say I have a variable named &quot;color,&quot;
and I'll set its value to the string black,
and let's say I have a function showColor,
and right now we'll say it takes no arguments,
and our body of our function is going to be this.
We're going to say &quot;var color = green.&quot;
What I'm going to do from inside our function is call console.log
and use the variable color.
On line 26 we created a variable called color.
Then we defined a function called showColor inside of which
we also defined another variable called color
and have given it another value.
The question is when we call showColor
what are we going to get?
Place your bets now.
Are we going to get black? Are we going to get green?
Are we going to get an error? What's going to happen?
Well, let's take a look, and we're back on our page here,
and if I refresh we see we get green.
Now, why does it do this?
Well, on line 26 we created a variable,
and we've created it at the global scope,
which means that we've created it outside of any function.
Now, what we've done on line 29 is created another variable called &quot;color.&quot;
However, the difference is we've created it in what we call a new scope,
and you can think of scope as sort of a name space for our variables.
Even though we already had a variable named color,
we've created a whole new layer or a whole new name space
that we can define new variables in.
And if we define new variables from inside a function
they will not collide with anything from a higher scope
including our global scope where our current color variable lives.
On line 29 it does not interact at all with the color that we've defined on line 26.
Instead it creates a brand-new variable that from within showColor
now the color variable will refer to that color green
and not the color black, and to show that assigning the variable color
equals green on line 29 does not interact with the color
from outside of our function after we call showColor
let's do console.log('Global color', color).
I'm going to change this console.log here,
and we'll add in another prefix here, and we'll say
our showColor color and pass it the color from inside of showColor.
So, now what we are doing is we are calling showColor,
which will execute the line 29, var color = green,
and then we'll inspect color from inside of our function,
and we'll see that it will be green, which we saw last time,
but let's see what happens after we call showColor,
and on line 37 again try to console.log the variable called &quot;color.&quot;
If we refresh we can see our showColor color is green,
and our global color is still black.
Now, does that mean from within a function we can't reach variables
that are at a higher scope?
Well, let's do another example.
Let's say &quot;var number = 1.&quot;
And let's say from within showColor here
we log our number, and let's do the same thing after we call our showColor.
We've defined a variable number at our global scope,
and when we call showColor we're reaching that number in our console.log
and logging its value.
Then afterwards we're also logging number once again on line 40,
so what happens?
We see that the number is 1 from inside of showColor,
and number is also 1 inside of global,
which means we're able to access higher level variables from within our function.
However, what would happen if we wanted to reach the global color
from within our function where we've already defined a local color variable?
Well, that's actually pretty difficult to do
because now that we've defined a local color and assigned it green
it's hard to reach that global color which was holding the value black.
Now, in our case since it is global there is a technique we can use,
but let's not look at that right now.
Essentially what we've done is we've shadowed the variable.
By giving a local variable the same name as a variable
in a higher scope we've made it inaccessible to us.
Now, really this is avoided by not giving variables
at different scopes the same name.
You can see we have no problem with number reaching up to the global scope,
but since color is defined at a closer scope
than the global scope, which we might want,
we're unable to reach it, and this is called shadowing.
Now, can we modify variables at a higher scope?
Let's say we want to say number now equals 2.
Now, what would happen?
If we refresh we can see that number has not only changed to 2
from inside of showColor but it's also changed at the global scope.
That's because on line 32 number refers to the exact variable
that's defined on line 27, so just like we can assign a value to a variable
from the global scope we can also do it from inside the local scope.
Now, why might this be a problem?
You'll remember when I talked about defining variables in the previous videos
that I said the var keyword is very important,
and here's why it's really important.
When we take a look here at our output we see that the showColor color is green,
but the global color remains black.
We talked about how they created a variable at a different scope.
But what happens if we forgot to put the var keyword in front of color here?
Well, that changes things.
We're no longer defining a new variable called &quot;color&quot;
at the local level.
Instead what we're doing is we're referring to the color variable
at the global scope and assigning to it and changing it,
so if we refresh we'll now see it's actually changed the global color,
and that can be very, very dangerous and very confusing to debug.
If you forget var when you meant to create a new variable
you might be actually changing the value of a variable at a higher level scope.
Once again, this is something that you can avoid by not shadowing your variables
or giving variables the same name at different level scopes.
That way you don't have to worry about which one is which,
but let's put var back in here.
Now, there's another curious property here.
What if we were to do this?
If we change and console.log our shape here,
and let's also console it from the global scope,
what would happen?
Well, you might think since shape is not defined at the global scope
it will define a new variable called shape at showColor,
but we'll see what happens is actually a little bit different.
If we refresh we can see the shape from inside showColor is square,
but also global has a variable called shape which is also square.
Now, this may appear to work in our code if we miss this error.
However, it might become very confusing because
every time we call showColor it will refer to the exact same shape instance
because what's happened here is we assigned to a variable
that we have not declared with a var keyword.
And what JavaScript does in this case is it creates
a global variable called shape and assigns it square
because it didn't know what level to define that variable,
so it went to global.
Now, this is a behavior that some consider to be a bug in JavaScript,
but ultimately it's just something that can be harmful,
and there's actually some settings that we can change
that will avoid this behavior in the future.
However, in JavaScript if we forget the var keyword
it creates this global variable, and while showColor
may seem to still work the way we want
we're now creating a new global variable,
and the implications of that may not be obvious
and may result in some  unusual bugs,
so that's why the var keyword is so vitally important.
If we were to put a var in front of that line here
this changes the meaning of our code entirely.
Now instead of creating a global shape with square
we've only created a local one, which means on line 45
where we log the shape from the global scope
we now get the correct output, which is a reference error
because we have not defined shape at the global scope.
And by trying to access it, that causes an error in JavaScript,
and that shows you that a function creates a brand-new scope
where whenever we use the var keyword
we're creating a variable only accessible from within this function call,
which means that we can create all the variables we want
inside of showColor without worrying about bleeding them out to the global scope
where they might be interacting with other things that are using that name
or just producing unwanted behavior.
We'll see how function scope can be useful in an upcoming video
where we talk about how functions can be used also
as a tool to define scopes.
In the next video we'll see why scope is so important
when we learn about anonymous functions.
[? Music ?] [Treehouse]