[Treehouse]
In the last video, we learned about methods
and the special value called this.
Now we'll learn how to control the value of this
with the methods call and apply.
So we saw how this can be bound to an object
by calling our method, like jim.name
or by using our square brackets
and calling it jim[&quot;greet&quot;] and invoking it with parentheses.
This will be bound to Jim,
or in this case, this will be bound to Nick,
which provides us some useful functions in that we can reuse
greet in several different objects
and this will provide a nice level of variability
where we can have the same method
be invoked on several different objects
and always have the correct but different behavior between them.
But we saw that there's a problem.
As soon as we de-reference or store a method into another variable,
we lose that binding of this to that object.
For instance, when we store jim.greet
into the variable called &quot;jimgreet&quot; on line 28,
the binding from greets this variable
loses its association with Jim.
So when we invoked it on line 29,
there's nothing for it to be bound to,
so by default, in JavaScript it's bound to the window variable,
which is not very useful.
But what happens if we have to call a function
as though it were a method on an object?
So here's one thing we could do.
Let's remove what is this.
We don't need this anymore, since we explored what this is when calling a normal function.
So if we go back and we refresh,
we can see we have three different things.
First we have &quot;Hello. I am James.&quot;
Which you remember is for Jim, where we assigned .name here.
So we can see that it gets the latest version
of this.name,
which would be jim.name in line 25's
invocation of greet,
and then we get Nick's greeting, which is &quot;Hello. I am Nick.&quot;
Now, what's interesting is we say, &quot;Hello. I am the window.&quot;
That's because remember that
in this invocation here,
[jimGreet], this is the window,
and so window.name
we assigned to the value &quot;the window.&quot;
However, window.name is a special property in JavaScript,
in the browser, in that it actually names
our physical window--
all of the chrome, the buttons, and everything.
It's actually referring to that actual window,
and so name doesn't get reset every time we change our browser.
We've actually named our window
so it persists as long as this window persists.
So to change it back we could do window.name=empty string.
If we refresh we now see what would be the default,
since the window name is now the empty string.
But on line 29, that's not what we want to do at all.
Instead we want [jimgreet] to be called
with the context of Jim,
meaning this will be bound to Jim.
And the way we can do that is through a special method
built onto all JavaScript functions called &quot;call.&quot;
So how do we do that?
Well, instead of just invoking the function with our parentheses,
[jimgreet], which is a function--
and a function is actually a type of object,
meaning it itself has these key value properties.
And one of those key value properties
that is on every function is one called &quot;call,&quot; C-A-L-L.
And this is a method which actually invokes itself.
So when we call it jimGreet.call,
it's going to literally call jimGreet.
But how this differs from normally invoking our function
is that there is an extra argument
added to the beginning of our method call.
So we'll say and that extra argument
is what value should be bound to this
in our invocation of this function.
So in our case, when we call a jimGreet,
we want this to be bound to Jim.
So if we refresh, we'll see now
that that third call has Jim bound to this,
and this is awesome because even though jim.greet
came from Jim, we can change what it is
on the fly.
For instance, if we want to call it with a context bound to Nick,
we can just do jimGreet.call,
pass in the Nick object,
and now this and greet will be bound to Nick,
so nick.name is Nick.
So if we refresh, we can see it's now Nick.
And in fact it really doesn't matter where we pass it to.
We can pass it an empty object,
and if we refresh we'll see &quot;I am undefined,&quot;
because an empty object doesn't have a value
for the key name,
and if we have an object like var obj equals the empty object--
which is curly brace open, curly brace closed--
with no key value pairs,
we try to access a key like name,
everything is undefined,
so that's why we get &quot;I am undefined.&quot;
It doesn't matter what we have here.
It's always going to be undefined.
Or we could go a step further and just define
as much of the object as we need to.
In our case, we'll say &quot;Amit.&quot;
And if we refresh we can see we say, &quot;Hello. I am Amit.&quot;
And that's great.
In fact, we don't even have to store this into a variable to use this
because it's available on any function.
So if we were to even call jim.greet.call[nick],
what's happening?
Well, we have the object Jim, and then we're getting
what's in the greet key, which is our function.
Our function has a call method that's built in,
which will invoke greet with a context
down to this.
Now, context should be Nick.
So we can just do hello. And now we see, &quot;Hello. I am Nick.&quot;
Now, besides call, there's another method
that's built in just like call that works almost the exact same way,
and that method is apply.
You'll see it's highlighted the same way call is in our editor.
In fact, in this example, they're exactly the same.
If we refresh, we get the exact same results.
How call and apply differ
is how they take arguments.
Now, our greet function, right now, doesn't contain any arguments,
but I'm going to change it around with a snap.
Now I've updated this function with a little bit more logic.
I added two parameters that we'll take.
First is the name of the person we're greeting,
and the second is our current mood.
Now lines 8 and 9 here are to make name and mood optional.
What we're doing is we're saying name equals.
If name exists, we'll just say name is name
and we'll not do anything.
However, if name is undefined or false,
we use the or operator,
and that's the two vertical pipes right here.
This means &quot;or&quot; in JavaScript.
So this expression means name equals either name or you.
If name is true, name or you will return name;
however, if it's false, it will take the right-hand side of or.
So this is a convenient way of saying
if something is false, provide a default value.
So if we pass in nothing, name would be undefined,
so we'd say undefined or, if it's undefined or false, give it you.
And the same thing for mood.
So basically, if we just call greet with no parameters,
we will get the name being you
and the mood being good.
So now that we've got those two parameters that are optional,
we changed our console.log here a little bit
to integrate those.
We're basically constructing a string by concatenating multiple things together,
and I've just broken it onto different lines to make it more readable.
So we'll say &quot;Hello&quot; to the name of the person we're greeting,
and that comes from up here, &quot;I am,&quot; and then my name
by saying this.name, and then finally
&quot;and I am in a&quot; blank, which will be mood--mood.
So let's just see how that starts off.
Considering that we haven't changed anything,
these should now say &quot;Hello, you. I am James,&quot;--or Nick or Amit--
&quot;and I am in a good mood.&quot;
Now there is a little something I want to change.
It looks like we should put a space right there,
just to alleviate where You and I are mixed together there.
There we go.
And now we have some parameters for greet.
And we can see how that works.
We could say, &quot;Hello, Ryan,&quot; and pass in a mood
and just say, &quot;awesome.&quot;
And one of our invocations here will now say,
&quot;Hello, Ryan. I am James, and I am in an awesome mood.&quot;
Well, in &quot;a&quot; awesome mood, but we're not going to change that to be correct.
We'll just go with the grammatical error that is standing there.
So how does this interact with call and apply?
Well, let's take a look at our code.
When we use the call method,
what we can do is just pass in our arguments after our first argument.
Remember that first argument is the context
of the object which will be bound to this inside of our call.
So after that, we can now list our arguments right after that.
So we could say, &quot;Hello, Matt.&quot;
and then pass in our next argument.
We'll say &quot;I'm in a bad mood.&quot;
So we'll refresh, and we'll see that says,
&quot;Hello, Matt. I am Amit, and I am in a bad mood.&quot;
I don't know why Amit would be in a bad mood around Matt,
but that's beside the point.
How apply is different is instead of passing in our individual arguments,
like Matt and bad,
we instead pass all of the arguments in as a array.
So apply will--strictly speaking--only take two arguments,
the first being the context, and the second is an array of arguments.
So Matt will be passed to the first argument and bad to the second
and so on and so forth.
So if we refresh, you can see the same thing works here.
And that's the only way call and apply differ from each other
in that call will take any variable number of arguments,
where the first one will be the context
and the rest of the arguments will be the
rest of the normal arguments of that function.
However, apply first takes the context object
and then takes a single array containing zero or more arguments
to be passed in.
Now this might seem like an arbitrary distinction;
however, apply being used this way provides us
a really, really useful way to dynamically call functions.
For instance, if we wanted to call a function with a set of arguments
and we don't know how long those are,
the obvious thing to do is anytime we have some variable number of arguments
is to put them in array.
So we can say our args equals Michael, and let's say happy.
Even if we tried to call jim.greet,
there's no way for us to easily
just pass in those args like this.
If we did it like that, then our args
array would be bound to name, here.
And there's no real way to explode that out.
Instead what we normally do when we have
a list of arguments stored stored in array,
is call jim.greet.apply,
and even though we have jim.greet here,
we still have to pass in the context,
so we'd have to say Jim and then args,
and it works.
Now, you'll recognize this when it comes to it.
It doesn't come up all the time, but sometimes you just end up
with an array of arguments, and you don't know how many items are in that array,
so you can't statically break out those arguments
in our code.
Instead, we have to dynamically do it,
and apply offers us a great tool to do that,
since it will take an array, which is variable,
and apply it to the function,
setting the parameters as needed.
So now we've seen how methods work,
but we're having a lot of duplication of our data between objects.
In the next video, we'll learn how to use prototypes to clean that up.
[Treehouse]