[? Music ?] [Treehouse]
So far we've seen what happens when we declare a variable
and define its value immediately.
Now we'll see what happens when we want to declare a variable
without giving it a value.
So far we've declared all of our variables using this format,
the key word bar, the name of our variable, in this case myVar,
equals and then some value.
Now, when we declare a variable, we actually do not need to initialize the value,
and that means we can actually leave off the last 2 parts here,
the value and equals sign, and simply be left with var
and then the name of our variable, in this case myVar.
What happens when we declare a variable in this way?
Let's save this out, jump into our browser.
Now we've run our page as we've refreshed it,
and if we actually test out in our JavaScript console down here
myVar, we'll see that the value that it gives us back is undefined.
Now, undefined represents a non-value that was never defined.
There's another non-value called null.
Undefined and null are very similar, but null can be used
when you simply want to indicate that a variable truly is empty
and that it's not simply empty by default.
How can we test to see if a variable is defined?
Well, we've declared myVar here, and its value is undefined,
so let's try to see if we can evaluate whether or not
it is undefined using a piece of code.
We're going to use console.log,
and that is built into our browser, and what this allows us to do,
as we've seen before, is print out text to our JavaScript console
that we have in the bottom of our page.
We simply pass it a value, and it will print it out to the console
that we have on our page.
To get a true or false value based on whether it's undefined,
what we can do is use the type of operator,
and that's typeof, and you'll see we have it highlighted here
because it's a key word in JavaScript.
The way typeof works is we use the typeof key word
and then the name of a variable, in this case, myVar.
If we pass in this, let's see what happens in our console.
If we refresh, we can now see this line here undefined.
So, when we do typeof and undefined variable,
we get the string undefined.
Now, if we wanted to test if a variable is undefined,
for instance, for use in an if statement,
we can use this expression, &quot;typeof myVar ===&quot;
and then the string &quot;undefined.&quot;
Now, what this is doing is it's taking the typeof myVar,
which in this case would be the string undefined,
and comparing it to another string undefined.
The 3 equal signs is the operator that will test for the equality
of both sides of it.
If we have the string undefined on the left and the string undefined
on the right, this will all evaluate to true.
Let's test it out.
And now we can see console.log now evaluates to true.
If you ever want to test to see if a variable is undefined,
that's how we can do it.
Now, you may see in some other code testing for undefined in a different way.
Let's try &quot;console.log,&quot;
and we'll do &quot;myVar,&quot;
and without the typeof operator we will compare it to undefined,
and this is undefined the key word, not the string.
Instead we're simply testing if myVar itself
is equal to undefined.
Now, if we test this out, it appears it's true,
and so you may think, &quot;Hey, that's an easier way to test for it.&quot;
&quot;Why don't we always do that?&quot;
Well, undefined in JavaScript is actually a bit of a quirky key word
in that it's not really a key word at all.
It's actually a variable that's set by JavaScript,
and because of that it's possible to accidentally overwrite
the value of undefined or perhaps intentionally overwrite the value of undefined
to mess up somebody else's code.
What happens if somewhere else in your code we said something like
&quot;undefined = true?&quot;
You may think that's pretty silly to be allowed, and it kind of is,
but this is something that can actually happen in your code,
so you need to be very careful when testing for undefined.
So, if undefined = true is somewhere in our code
and we run it, instead of true true now we get true false,
so that's why we can't trust the actual undefined value that we have here.
Now, there are ways that we could enforce that our undefined is untampered with,
however, it's best practice just to use typeof myVar
is equal to the string undefined.
That way you can be pretty sure that myVar is truly undefined
and undefined itself, if its value has been tampered with,
it doesn't matter.
We talked a little bit about how undefined represents an empty value,
meaning that it hasn't been set to.
But what about null?
For instance, we could say &quot;var x = null,&quot;
and null is a key word that means nothing or empty.
Both null and undefined are what we call falsy values.
If we remember, in an if statement if we have a falsy value
it will not execute, so we could, for instance, say
&quot;myVar,&quot; and in the if block here
we'll do &quot;console.log If,&quot; and we'll use an else here,
and in the else block we'll do &quot;console.log Else.&quot;
Now we'll see which of these two get printed to our code.
In this case, we can see else because myVar has the value undefined,
and let's see what happens if we put an x.
Again, we see else, and that's because null and undefined
are both falsy values like false or the number 0.
Now, because undefined and null are so similar,
oftentimes we want to check if a value is either null or undefined.
But sometimes we want to do something different
if it is actually false or the value is 0.
If we want to check for either of the empty values null or undefined,
one easy way we could do this is to do our variable
== null.
Now, you may think that only works for null, but let's check it out.
Right now we have x == null,
and as you might expect, if we run it
we see the if statement executes, and that's because x is null
and null == null makes sense that it would be true.
Null is null.
But let's see what happens if we do myVar.
Does myVar = null?
Well, it's undefined, so you'd think it might not,
but if we refresh, we see that it does.
That's because the == or double equals operator
is not strict in how it compares things.
Sometimes it will sort of change the value when it evaluates it.
For instance, undefined and null are so similar
that the double equals operator considers them
to be equivalent.
I'm going to comment out this undefined = true
for the purposes of demonstration here so we have the true value of undefined
available to us, and if we were to check undefined
== null we see that it evaluates to true.
You'll remember that there's also a triple equals operator,
and this is the strict equality operator.
And this will not change values if they're close enough to each other,
so if we do undefined === null,
we'll see it's false because strictly they're not equal,
but conceptually they kind of are, which is why double equals
returns true and triple equals returns false.
In most cases, you want to use the triple equals because you don't want
any unexpected changing of variables when comparing them.
But in this case, when checking something double equals null,
it has the convenience of allowing  you to check if it's null or undefined.
This is a special use case that you can use if you ever want to check
that a value is either null or undefined
as opposed to null, undefined, false, or 0.
Up next, we'll see how variables are accessible at different points in our program
by learning about variable scope.
[? Music ?] [Treehouse]