[? Music ?] [Treehouse]
So far we've seen the different ways that we can define numbers in JavaScript.
Now we'll take a look at a few of the mathematical operators
that we can use to actually work with those  numbers.
At this point, we should be pretty familiar with how to actually get numbers
into our variables or into our JavaScript code.
Now what can we do with them?
Well, the most common thing we'll do is arithmetic operations
like adding them, subtracting them, dividing them and multiplying them.
And we've already seen a little bit of this before,
but let's just go over the operators that we could use.
We'll create a variable called &quot;o,&quot;
and we can do something like 1 + 2.
Using the + operator will simply add the 2 operands together,
in this case, 1 and 2.
Or we could replace this with a variable,
1 + k, or we could do j + k.
If we take a look at the value of o, it's going to be j + k, which is 42.
Or we could just do 1 + k, and o would be 24.
And of course, if we did 1 + 2, we get 3.
Subtraction works exactly like you would expect it to.
If we wanted to do 10 - 7, we use the dash character as our subtraction operator,
and the value of p will of course be 3.
The + and - operators work both with our whole numbers
and our floating point, so we could do 1 + 2.4
and 10 - 7.3, and we'll get the values 3.4 and 2.7 as usual.
Nothing too crazy there.
Multiplication and division work pretty much the same way.
If we want to multiply 3 times 4,
the multiplication operator is the star,
and on most keyboards, that's the asterisk, which is Shift and the number 8.
3 times 4, q should have the value of 12, which it does.
Again, we could do 3 times 4.2,
and if we refresh and check q, then we get 12.6.
Again, we see it's not exactly 12.6.
It's 12.6, then a lot of zeros and a 1.
It's very near 6, but again, this is the issue
with multiplying our floating point numbers together.
Sometimes we get these rounding errors, and we're just going to
sort of deal with that right now.
For division, we use the forward slash operator.
We'll set a variable r, and if we do 16 / 8,
we will get 2.
Now, there's something very important to note about division.
In some languages, like I mentioned before, when we have integers or whole numbers
and we divide them, and they don't come out evenly,
there are 2 things that could happen.
Let's say, for instance, we divided 15 / 10.
The actual answer would be 1.5,
but in some languages, because both of our operands here were
whole numbers or integers, they would want to return an integer,
in which case it would round down the number to 1.
However, in JavaScript, all of our numbers are the same floating point type
even if they look like whole numbers, so 15 / 10
is going to in fact give us the answer 1.5.
Now we'll see how we could round our answer down
if we wanted to in the next video,
but now just remember that division is always going to possibly return you
a floating point number like 1.5.
The next operator you may not be very familiar with using
in typical mathematical operations, but in programming
it's a pretty important operator, and it's called the modulo operator,
and it's represented by the percentage sign.
If we take s, and we take 15 mod or modulo using the percentage sign, 10,
instead of giving us the answer to 15 / 10,
instead it's going to give us the remainder of dividing 15 by 10.
If you divide 15 into 10, you get 1 with a remainder of 5,
so 15 mod 10 will return us 5, hopefully.
If we refresh, take a look at s, we get 5.
Again, if we did 16 mod 10
and take a look at s, we get 6.
26 mod 10 will also be 6 because 26 goes into 10 two times
with a remainder of 6.
And if we had the number 30, because 10 goes into 30  three times
with no remainder, the modulo answer of s would be 0.
Now, a little bit later on we'll see some practical applications of this operator,
but it's important to know that you can use it to get the remainder
of the division operation.
Now we can combine these operators together.
What happens if we do 1 + 2 * 3 / 4?
Well, it really depends on something called the order of operations.
You probably learned about order of operations in your math classes in school,
and the same thing applies in JavaScript.
There is an order of operations to the different operands here.
If there wasn't an order, for instance, we would get the number 1 + 2,
which would be 3, times 3, which would be 9.
Then 9 / 4.
However, that's not the order of operations in arithmetic.
Instead multiplication and division operations
always come before addition and subtraction operations,
and this is no different, so instead what we get is
2 times 3, which is 6, divided by 4,
which is 1.5, and then finally we do the addition operation,
so t should be 2.5.
If we refresh and check out the value of t,
we get 2.5.
Now what if we wanted, for instance, 1 + 2 to be calculated before
the multiplication and the division?
Just like in normal arithmetic, we can use parentheses to group them.
Parentheses will always be evaluated before any other operators,
so if we wanted 1 + 2 to be evaluated first,
we can simply wrap the subexpression 1 + 2 in parentheses.
Now 1 + 2, which will be 3, will be multiplied times 3
and then divided by 4, so the result will be 9 divided by 4,
and if we check it out, we get 2.25, which is 9 divided by 4.
Multiplication and division have the same level precedence
in our order of operations.
Similarly, addition and subtraction have the same level.
When 2 operators have the same level,
the mathematical operators are what we call left associative,
meaning that if they are at the same level,
it will go from left to right, so in this case
it will multiply our 3 times 3
and then divide by 4.
If, for instance, we wanted to divide 3 divided by 4 before we multiply them,
we could, again, wrap those in parentheses,
but it should lead to the same result, 2.25.
But any time you want to control the order of operations,
parentheses are what allow you to proceed the normal order of operations
of our operators.
Now, there are a lot of other operators besides our arithmetic operators,
and JavaScript has a well-defined order of operations on all of these,
so if  you're ever curious as to which operators will be evaluated first
in a complicated expression, you can refer to the operator precedence table
to determine exactly what will happen.
[Operator Precedence Table] [developer.mozilla.org/en/JavaScript/Reference/Operators/Operator_Precedence]
Again, you can always use parentheses to control the order of the operations
to how you want them to work.
Up next, we'll see how we can compare 2 numbers together in JavaScript.
[? Music ?] [Treehouse]