[? Music ?] [Treehouse]
In JavaScript, we can actually extract numbers out of strings
that have numeric characters in them.
Let's see how that works.
So far every time we've created a number,
we've used what we call a literal notation,
meaning that in our JavaScript code, our numbers are literally represented as code.
However, sometimes we may want to get numbers out of, perhaps, a string.
If we had a string with the value 197 in it,
this doesn't do us much good for, let's say, arithmetic operations.
We can't add other numbers to it because it's a string,
so how do we get a real number out of a string?
Well, one method we could do if we want a whole number
is to use a method called &quot;parseInt,&quot;
and this is a built-in function to JavaScript,
so the way we use it is to type in &quot;parse,&quot; all lowercase, with a capital &quot;I,&quot;
&quot;nt,&quot; and then we open up parentheses, placing the number inside.
Now, this is the easiest way to do this, and the &quot;Int&quot; stands for integer.
Remember earlier I was talking about the difference between integers and floats.
However, remember that numbers don't have this distinction
when they're represented in JavaScript.
However, there are 2 different functions, parseInt and parseFloat,
which will return  you either a whole number
or the number with the included floating point precision.
This is just a convenience because usually you either want to
pull out a whole number or the whole floating point number out of a string.
Let's just focus on pulling a whole number or an integer out of a string.
If we take our j, I have &quot;parseInt(&quot;197&quot;),&quot;
and we refresh our browser, type in &quot;j,&quot; and we get 197, the number, not the string.
We could do &quot;j + 2,&quot; and we get 199.
This is how we can get a number out of a string.
Now what would happen if our number was something like 012?
We saw what happened when this was a literal,
but let's see what happens in parseInt.
If we refresh, type in &quot;j,&quot; we get the actual number 10.
Now, again, this may seem confusing because
we think it would be 12, but remember, the leading 0 represents it as an octal form.
Now what would happen if we type in &quot;019?&quot;
Well, it kind of depends. Let's check it out.
We get the number 1, so we get some strange behavior.
To solve this problem, if we know that our representation is a decimal representation,
we want to add a second argument to parseInt, which is the radix,
which is the base of the number system we want to parse.
Normally we want to parse the decimal,
so our second argument would be 10, meaning that our number
is base 10, so 019 should be the number 19.
If we refresh, type in &quot;j,&quot; now we should see that it's the number 19.
Now, this is something that you'll learn after making this mistake
a lot of times in JavaScript.
Here's the lesson.
Any time you use parseInt to get a number out of a string,
you really want to add the second argument of 10
unless you're specifically working in a different base
because you may not know what the actual string representation of a number is
because it may be stored in a variable, or it may come from a user or another situation.
You don't know if it will have the weird properties, for instance, leading with a 0.
By adding the second argument of base 10,
you're assured that any time it parses an integer
it will always be done in base 10, and then the format of the actual
number in the string won't matter.
It won't change the base that it's parsed.
To make this even more confusing, if we just did parseInt 012,
in some implementations it will represent it as an octal,
and its sum a decimal.
Even though you can get away with not putting the second argument parseInt in,
you always want to because you're being very specific about
what type of number you're parsing out of your string,
so just always use &quot;,10&quot; when parsing an integer out of a string.
Now we could use parseInt and the radix operator to do some other interesting things.
For instance, if we wanted to parse binary out of it,
we could use the base 2 as a binary operator,
which means the only digits we could use in our string are 0 and 1,
and if you had a binary string of some sort, for instance, 0s and 1s,
and let's change this to k, and if we refresh and type in &quot;k,&quot;
we'll see that the 010111 representation in base 2 is the number 23.
So this radix argument is an arbitrary number,
so we could do 3, and that will change what k is.
Very rarely do you work in a base 3 number system,
but you can change it to 8 for octal and get the correct numbers.
But most of the time you're going to want your radix operator to be 10,
so what happens if we do parseInt with some non-digits in it?
Let's say we do 23 people,
and remember, any time we do a parseInt, you always want to add a radix here of 10.
If we refresh and take a look at l, we'll see it's 23.
It parsed it out pretty well, however, what if we did
&quot;there are 23 people?&quot;
And we refresh.
We get an interesting value called &quot;NaN,&quot; and NaN stands for &quot;not a number.&quot;
And this is a value that's used in JavaScript to represent a value
that is not a number.
Now NaN has some interesting properties.
If you, for instance, try to add a number to NaN,
so we'll take l, which is not a number,
and add 14 to it, we get not a number.
In fact, if we do any type of operation to not a number,
the result is always not a number.
If at any point in time you do an operation like parseInt
that could return not a number,
you want to check for it because any operations that you do after that
will result in those results being not a number all the way up.
You may see NaN show up in your JavaScripts when you don't expect it.
That means at some point, not a number showed up.
So how do we check for not a number?
We know l is going to be not a number,
so you might think we could do &quot;===  NaN.&quot;
See, it highlights because not a number is something that we can use as a literal,
but what happens if we actually do this?
And we refresh.
We get false.
But we know l is NaN, and for some reason
if we compare the two of them, we get false.
Maybe it's because we're using our strict equality operator,
but what if we just try 2 equals?
Well, we get false again,
and that's because not a number has a curious property
of not being equal to itself,
so we can see that even comparing
the JavaScript variable l to itself returns false.
You may be tempted to use that to detect not a number,
but what you want to do is use a function that's built into JavaScript called isNaN.
The way we do that is type in &quot;isNaN.&quot;
And this takes a parameter, and if we pass an l, which is not a number,
we'll see it's true, so NaN is a very weird value
because it doesn't equal itself or any other number
and has a special function for testing if it is itself.
And the last function I want to talk about here is called parseFloat,
and it acts very similar to parseInt,
and we'll say &quot;parseFloat(&quot;123.456&quot;).&quot;
And now the number m will be 123.456,
and this has the same properties, so if we have stuff after the number,
like &quot;is a strange number,&quot;
we can see that m still works.
However, if we lead with some other stuff, &quot;this number,&quot;
we'll see that, again, parseFloat returns not a number.
For parseInt and for parseFloat to work, it must start with a number,
and then anything after the number really won't affect it
so long as your string starts with something that could be parsed as a number.
With parseFloat, we don't have to add the second argument of our radix
because parseFloat will work in base 10
really no matter what, so if we did this and checked our value of m,
we still get 123.456.
So parseInt and parseFloat are the 2 functions you would use
to get  a number out of a string.
So now we've seen the different ways we can create numbers
or even parse them out of a string.
Up next, we'll look at the mathematical operators we can use
on our numbers.
[? Music ?] [Treehouse]