[? Music ?] [Treehouse]
Strings in JavaScript can be compared,
meaning we can tell if 1 string is less than,
greater than, or equal to another string.
Let's see how that works.
Now that we've seen how to create and get the properties of strings,
there's one more thing that we'll generally do with strings very often,
and that is compare them.
When we compare 2 strings, what we're asking is
whether the 2 strings are equal or whether 1 string
has a greater value than another string.
Let's begin with testing for equality strings.
I've commented out our previous code so we have fewer
console.logs to sift through while we're experimenting with JavaScript strings.
In order to test the equality of 2 strings,
first we need to have 2 strings, and then we're going to use
the equals operator.
Let's grab 2 strings.
Let's grab our first string,
and we'll say &quot;Hello.&quot;
And our second string we'll do a lowercase &quot;hello.&quot;
And the way we can test for equality is simply by doing this.
We're going to do it in the context of an if statement,
so we'll say &quot;if (first === second).&quot;
The 3 equals here means is equal to.
And more specifically, it means is strictly equal to.
There is another similar operator in JavaScript which is 2 equals signs.
The difference between 2 equals signs and 3 equals signs
is that when you use only 2 equals signs
JavaScript will sometimes change the type of one of the operands
if it will allow it to match the other operand.
For instance, you might be able to compare a string
with the number 13 in it to the actual number 13
and the double equals would return true,
but the triple equals will only return true if both sides are strings
and they are equivalent strings.
So, we're going to use 3 equals signs whenever we want to do this.
This will help reduce errors in our JavaScript programs.
In our if statement, we'll say console.log(&quot;The strings are equal&quot;).
And we'll put an else clause here,
and we'll say console.log(&quot;The strings are different&quot;).
Right now we're comparing first, which is the string &quot;Hello&quot; with a capital H
to second, which is &quot;hello&quot; with a lowercase H.
So what is the expected result?
Well, let's save this out,
return to our browser, and we'll refresh.
And we'll see that the strings are different,
and that's because first and second are 2 different strings
because first has a capital H, and second has a lowercase h.
The equality operator takes into account the differences in case in the letters.
They'll only be equal if they are the exact same letters
in the same case.
Sometimes we want to compare strings without being sensitive
to the case.
The best way to handle this is to use the methods that we saw earlier,
either 2 uppercase or 2 lowercase.
Generally, 2 lowercase is used in this use case,
so let's try this out.
What we'll do is we'll take our first string
and call the 2 lowercase method.
And now the left-hand side will be whatever the first string was
but all lowercase.
And to be safe, we'll do the other side as well
to lowercase.
And now what we have is a comparison of the strings
that is insensitive to the case of the letters inside of those strings.
If we save that out and refresh,
we see now that the strings are equal.
Any time that you want to do a string comparison
that is insensitive to case, the easiest way
is to lowercase both of the strings you are comparing.
Now besides the equality operator, there are 4 other comparisons
we can use between the strings.
This includes less than, greater than,
less than or equal to, and greater than or equal to.
The difference between less than and less than or equal to
is that less than will only return true if the left-hand side
is less than the right-hand side.
However, less than or equal to will return true
if the left-hand side is less than the right-hand side
or if the 2 sides are equal.
Let's just focus on less than right now because
less than is the opposite of greater than, and it's pretty easy
to understand how the JavaScript strings will be evaluated
once you understand less than.
What I've done here is I've created a function called &quot;compare.&quot;
And this is just to help us experiment
with the different ways strings will compare to each other.
It simply takes 2 strings and it will console.log
both the message describing those strings
with the less than between them, and the second argument is
the actual comparison of a is less than b.
Let's try out a few strings.
We'll use the compare function we just created,
and let's compare the string &quot;a&quot;
to the string &quot;b.&quot;
Now this will print out true if the string &quot;a&quot; is in fact less than the string &quot;b,&quot;
and based on the alphabetical order, we would expect that to be true,
so let's try it out.
If we refresh, &quot;a&quot; is less than &quot;b&quot; is true.
What would happen if we took a lowercase a
and compared it to an uppercase A?
Let's check it out in the browser.
And we'll see lowercase a less than uppercase A is false.
And that's because of the way strings are encoded
and compared.
Any uppercase letter is always going to be
less than any lowercase letter.
That's because the characters that we use in our string
are roughly based on the ASCII table.
This ASCII table assigns each character that could be in our string
a value, and when we compare strings,
it uses the values of each of those characters to compare them.
If we were to look inside of this table for the lowercase a,
we'll see its decimal value is equivalent to 97
where the uppercase A is equivalent to the decimal value 65.
That's why a lowercase a would actually be greater
than an uppercase A.
And this type of comparison will work for all the characters that we see here.
For instance, an open square bracket would be less than
a closing square bracket.
We can compare more than single characters.
We can compare longer strings like &quot;compare('apples', 'oranges')&quot;
and the way the comparison will be created is JavaScript
will look at the first character in each string.
If the first character of the left-hand side is less than the
first character of the right-hand side, then less than is true.
It only needs to go to the subsequent letters
if the letters it has looked at so far are equivalent.
For example, comparing apples to applications.
What will determine which is greater or which is less than
will actually be the &quot;e&quot; in apples and the &quot;i&quot; in applications.
And we can see what the results will be here.
Both of them, apples comes before applications
because in apples versus oranges, a comes before o,
and in apples versus applications, e comes before i.
Now what happens if one string is a substring of the other?
For instance, if we compare app to apples.
We can see that the comparison will go through a, p and p.
However, the left-hand side runs out of letters,
meaning that the left-hand side is smaller
than the right-hand side.
Finally, if we do compare 2 of the same strings
like &quot;hello&quot; and &quot;hello,&quot;
we'll see once again that hello is not less than hello because they are equal.
However, if we modified our compare function and set it to use less than
or equal to, both in our description and our actual comparison,
we'll see that hello is less than or equal to hello because
hello and hello are equal, and that is the only way that less than
and less than or equal to  are different.
Conversely, greater than and greater than or equal to will work the same way
as we've seen only in the reverse order.
Now you should be familiar with strings in JavaScript.
There is still more to learn, but we'll be seeing more about strings
as we learn about the other types in JavaScript.
[? Music ?] [Treehouse]