[? Music ?] [Treehouse]
Functions are an important part of JavaScript.
They're a way that we can store code to call later in our programs.
In these videos we'll be learning how to use functions in JavaScript.
Now we're going to begin learning about JavaScript functions.
You'll remember functions from Introduction to Programming
and how they allow us to store code into reusable bits that we can call later.
Now this is really exciting because as we learn JavaScript functions
we'll begin to be able to interact with our web page in a more fun way.
Rather than just logging to the console we'll be able to start
actually interacting with page elements because the way the browser works
is it uses functions and events to actually interact with the page.
We'll see a little bit more about that as we come up on it,
but I just want to show you that as we learn functions
we're actually going to start doing some interesting things and get
out of the console and into the page.
But before we do that let's take a little review on what functions are
and how they work in JavaScript.
We'll be working on this simple HTML page that has a single
JavaScript page loaded into it, and we'll be editing
those two as we learn about functions.
We have our index.html page, which just has some basic styling,
and we're including our functions.js,
and our functions.js is empty.
The basic way we can create a function in JavaScript is using the function keyword,
and here is the sort of basic syntax we can use to generate
a function that will take some sort of action when we call it.
We start with the word &quot;function,&quot; and you'll notice it highlights blue because
function is a JavaScript keyword.
The next thing we're going to do in this syntax is give the function a name,
and the name should be descriptive of what the function does or what it returns.
In our case I'm going to make a very simple function that calls
console.log with some information, and I'm going to have it say &quot;sayHello.&quot;
So, I'm going to call this function &quot;sayHello.&quot;
We can name our function using the same rules that we've used for naming variables.
We can have letters or numbers so long as it doesn't begin with a number,
and the same special characters apply, so this sayHello
would be a valid variable name, and so it's also a valid function name.
We have function sayHello, and I'm going to put a space,
and then I'm going to list the parameters or arguments that my function can take.
A function is able to take in different arguments
that will be variables passed in that allow us to change the behavior
of our actual function call each and every time we call it.
Right now I'm going to leave it blank, being empty parentheses,
but even though it's taking no arguments we still need to have
our parentheses in place.
I have our parentheses, and then I'll put another space,
and we'll begin our curly braces, and the curly braces delineate the body of our function,
so we'll open it up right there.
And now we have a basic empty function,
and I want it to actually do something, so let's make it very basic
and use the familiar console.log, and it will say
&quot;Hello World!&quot;
We have a basic function called &quot;sayHello,&quot;
and the body of that function is a piece of code that says &quot;console.log(&quot;Hello World!&quot;).&quot;
So what happens if we run this in our page?
Let's flip to our browser.
I'm going to refresh, and let's open up our console.
And right now we see nothing in our console.
However, if we start typing &quot;sayHello&quot;
you'll see it autocompleted, and what we can do is actually call this function.
And the way we call the function is by giving its name
and then using parentheses immediately after it.
Now, these parentheses are where we pass in the values we want to
assign to our arguments, but remember sayHello doesn't take any arguments yet,
so it will be an open parenthesis and a closed parenthesis,
and if we execute that code you'll notice that the console.log
has written &quot;Hello World!&quot; to our console, and we see this extra line here saying &quot;undefined.&quot;
You'll remember that our console will tell us the value of the previous expression given.
Now, when we called sayHello it's evaluated to undefined,
and we'll see what that means a little bit later,
but basically every time we call a function some sort of value is evaluated from it,
and we can control what that is.
But in our case we haven't returned anything,
and we'll see what that means in a second, but right now
we can just say that when we call sayHello
the value that it evaluates to is undefined.
We can call it in our console, but we can also call our function
anywhere in our code, so what we can do is do &quot;sayHello,&quot;
and now that we've called sayHello after we've defined sayHello
if we refresh our page immediately we should see Hello World! logged to our screen.
The benefit of this is now instead of just calling console.log(&quot;Hello World!&quot;)
we can call it multiple times.
If we want to say &quot;Hello World!&quot; in several places in our code
we can reuse this sayHello call.
If we save out our script and we refresh the browser
we'll now see that every time we called sayHello our console.log code has run.
Now, this isn't a very useful example.
We're really just changing one line of code to be
wrapped in a function that we can call later, and that may be helpful,
but really where functions are useful are that they can take arguments
and return values, so let's change our sayHello function around.
Let's say instead of saying &quot;Hello World!&quot; we wanted to say somebody's name.
Well, that means every time we call sayHello
we need to pass in a different name,
so that's what arguments are for, and our arguments are defined
after the name of our function.
These are going to be named like normal variables,
and they'll act very much like normal variables within our function scope.
Let's say our sayHello function will take an argument name.
Now we have a name variable that's useful inside of our function,
and let's see what happens if we add name to our console.log.
Now, if we refresh we'll see Hello World! in undefined.
That's because we've defined an argument called &quot;name&quot; in our sayHello function,
but we have not passed it in to any of our calls.
Let's actually go down and change our first call here
and pass in an argument, and we'll say &quot;sayHello(&quot;Jim&quot;).&quot;
What will happen is when we call sayHello with Jim
when we actually execute the code inside of sayHello
name will hold the value of Jim because that's what we passed in
in this particular function implication,
which means when we do console.log(&quot;Hello World!,&quot; name)
in our first invocation name will be Jim,
so we should see Hello World! and Jim.
And that's exactly what we see.
Now, we can have multiple arguments being passed to our sayHello
by separating them by commas.
What if I don't want to say hello but instead have a different greeting?
What I could do is create another argument called &quot;greeting.&quot;
Instead of saying &quot;Hello World!&quot; let's delete the hello,
and the first thing we'll log is our greeting,
and let's make sure there's a space there.
What happens now?
If I refresh we'll see &quot;undefined,&quot; &quot;world,&quot; and &quot;Jim.&quot;
Now, I'm going to change this console.log around.
Instead of passing in different arguments to console.log
let's create a string by simply joining our variables together
with the concatenation operator here, the + operator.
Now we should get a very similar result.
We just have a string.
Now, we're getting undefined showing up in our strings because
our greeting is not being passed to any of our invocations of sayHello
and because most of our invocations don't have name,
so what I'm going to do is I'm going to go ahead and just delete these ones right here.
In this invocation I will pass in a second argument, and we'll go ahead and
just say &quot;Greetings.&quot;
And so if we go back and we refresh we now see &quot;Greetings World!&quot; and &quot;Jim.&quot;
But what happens if I don't want to pass in a greeting?
Well, let's do another sayHello,
and we'll pass in a name but no greeting argument.
Well, in JavaScript even though we defined our function and it takes 2 arguments
we can pass any number of arguments we want when we actually call it.
If we call too few arguments any arguments that don't have a value
will have the value undefined within the function,
and if we call too many arguments, well,
there's just no argument name to attach to that value.
We can still access those extra values passed in,
but we'll see how to do that a little bit later.
What happens right now?
Well, if we only pass Jim, greeting will be bound to undefined,
and given the code we should see &quot;undefined World! Jim,&quot;
and that's not what I want, so we can add a little bit of code here
and say &quot;if&quot;--and the way we can test to make sure
greeting is undefined is we could say &quot;type of greeting === undefined.&quot;
And now we have this if clause, which we've seen before,
and so if we have greeting being undefined
what we can do is we can say &quot;greeting = Hello.&quot;
What we've done here is effectively created a default value for our greeting parameter.
If we call sayHello with only 1 argument
greeting will be undefined, which means we'll define it to be hello.
Let's see how that changes our code.
We'll save it out, and we'll refresh,
and now we can see &quot;Hello World! Jim.&quot;
We've seen how functions can take inputs called arguments.
In the next video we'll see how the function can provide an output
called the return value.
[? Music ?] [Treehouse]