[??] [Treehouse]
So far, we've created all of our functions with explicit names.
However, we can create functions without names called anonymous functions.
So far, we've defined our functions using what we call the named function syntax,
and it goes a little something like this.
We enter the keyword function, give it a name like myFunction,
give it the parameters that it will take, the arguments in parentheses here,
and then give it a function body.
And then later, we can call myFunction like so.
This named function is only 1 way that we can create a function in JavaScript.
Functions are just like any other value in JavaScript.
Much like arrays, numbers, and strings,
they can be stored into variables,
and that's kind of what's happening in this named function syntax.
myFunction is really just a variable that holds a function with some code in it.
However, there's a different way that we could go about doing this.
Instead of beginning with the myFunction keyword,
we can actually store it into a variable.
So let's create a var called myFunction.
And again, variable names are following the same rules as function names,
so why not just store it into a variable?
So we're creating a variable called myFunction,
and we're assigning it what?
Well, we can use the keyword function,
but instead of putting a name here, we'll skip it altogether
and move straight to the arguments by putting a space, parentheses--
in our case we'll take no arguments--and then the body of a function.
And let's just put some simple body here like console.log('myFunction was called').
So now what we have is we have defined a function
and stored it into myFunction, the variable.
And if we call myFunction just like we do any normal function,
we should get a very familiar result.
So let's refresh, and we can see myFunction was called.
We can just treat myFunction like we have any other function.
Just call it. It has return values, it takes arguments.
It's almost indistinguishable from the previous syntax that we used.
Since we don't give this function a name in the same way that we did before,
we call this an anonymous function.
We use the function keyword, define the arguments,
and define the body of the function all without giving it a specific name.
You can think of that as a named function
because we immediately stored it into a variable that has a name,
but that doesn't always have to be what we do with our anonymous functions.
Let's say I want to create another function that's going to call a function twice.
So since I'm creating a function, I can either use the anonymous function
that we assigned into a variable or use a named function.
In most cases, the difference is almost indistinguishable.
However, there are some subtle differences,
and so it's a matter of style choice.
I usually prefer to store my functions as anonymous functions inside variables.
However, I'll show you in a moment why a named function might be preferable.
Let's just say var callTwice =
and we'll take a function.
And the argument I want to pass to it is actually going to be another function.
Like I said before, functions are just like any other value in JavaScript.
They can be stored into variables and passed around.
So we'll say (targetFunction) is the name of our parameter,
and in the body of our function, since I have targetFunction,
this should be holding a function value,
which means that we can call the function by simply adding parentheses to the end.
And we'll say that it will call targetFunction with no properties twice.
So now what do I want to do?
I'm going to remove this myFunction here
and instead I'm going to call the function that I have stored and callTwice.
I do that by simply opening parentheses,
and now I need to pass it the argument that will be stored into targetFunction.
Well, my callTwice can only take functions as arguments,
and I already have a function stored into a variable called myFunction.
So let's see what happens.
You'll notice when I typed in myFunction here, I left off the parentheses.
I did not say myFunction, parenthesis open, parenthesis close.
That would be completely different from what I want to do.
If I left this code in place, what I would be doing is before I pass it to callTwice,
I'd be calling myFunction.
And remember, calling myFunction will evaluate to the return value,
which in my case, since there is no return value, would be undefined.
So targetFunction in callTwice would be the value undefined.
But if I don't put these parentheses, instead of calling myFunction,
I'm actually passing the value that's stored in myFunction the variable,
and that's an actual function object.
That function object is then assigned to targetFunction inside callTwice,
and targetFunction is called twice.
So let's see the behavior of that.
As you might guess, myFunction was called twice. That's pretty useful.
Just to show you that the same thing would have worked
if we had used the named function syntax,
I'm going to change this to myFunction.
So if we go back and refresh, we can see myFunction was called.
Now, why might this be useful?
Here's the reason that a named function might be more useful to you,
especially in development, as compared to assigning an anonymous function
into a variable.
Let's say I did something like undeclaredVariable.
When I actually call this, it will actually try to find the variable called undeclaredVariable,
which there is none.
And in JavaScript, that will result in a reference error, which we've seen before.
So let's see what happens.
We get &quot;Uncaught ReferenceError: undeclaredVariable is not defined.&quot;
This is where the debugging comes in handy.
In the console, it will give us a little bit of information about where this error came from.
For instance, we can see the type of error it is--a reference error--
as well as some description right here.
We also get the line number where it comes from, which is well linked right in here
so we can jump right to the code.
But sometimes that's not enough information for us.
If we called myFunction multiple times,
we want to find out exactly which call of myFunction raised that error.
This little disclosure triangle here will open up what's called the call stack.
Every function that we call is called by another function or an outer function.
And so starting at the top is closest to where it actually got called.
So since the error happened inside of myFunction, we see this name here,
and we see that myFunction was called inside of callTwice.
Right now in Chrome, it looks like it's actually being quite smart about this.
In some browsers, however, if we had defined our function in the anonymous sense--
that is, say, myFunction;
don't forget the var, which is very important--
and remove this actually named part of our function,
now we can see that the call stack has given us myFunction
and callTwice as names that help us out.
However, the top level is anonymous function.
In some browsers, if we had gone with var myFunction
and assigned it an anonymous function,
it will not have that name associated with it
and our tools wouldn't be able to tell us very easily where or what function it is.
However, later versions of more modern browsers are now really smart about this
and can detect when you're assigning an anonymous function into a variable
and it will keep track of that name for you whenever it can.
There are still cases where it can't quite do that,
and we'll see that in a moment.
So let's go back to callTwice here.
We've seen we're able to pass in an argument that's stored in a variable,
which can either be stored in the variable using var myFunction =
the anonymous function
or by using a named function.
However, we can use an anonymous function directly
without worrying about assigning it to a variable.
In some cases, we may only want to use this function this 1 time,
and storing it into a variable is unnecessary just to call this.
Well, since an anonymous function is really just an expression that returns a function,
we can just use that anonymous function.
So instead of giving it a name, we'll just pass into callTwice
the expression that we use to build a function--
that is, the function keyword, the parameters, and the body.
Usually, we want to split the body onto multiple lines,
and that is totally okay to do.
We've opened up our curly brace.
Inside of here we're talking about our function that we're defining inside of this callTwice call.
And then we close our function with these curly braces,
and this last parentheses here is the closing parentheses of the callTwice call.
So what happens is when we call this code, it'll evaluate this function definition
and then it'll pass that function into callTwice.
So we can do console.log(&quot;Hello from anon function&quot;).
And so if we refresh now, we see we get twice Hello from anonymous function.
So let's see what happens if we do undeclaredVariable here.
We get &quot;undeclaredVariable is not defined.&quot;
This is what we tried to demonstrate in the first time.
If we unravel this, now we can see the call stack is slightly less helpful.
We have anonymous function, which was called from callTwice.
And the reason it can't give us a name
is because there really is no name for this function.
This is quite literally an anonymous function,
and JavaScript can't figure out a name for it because we didn't assign it into a variable
or give it a name.
Now, if we wanted to change that, we can do something like this.
We can do (function namedFunction) and give it a name
just like we had normally done in our named function syntax.
Let's see how this differs here.
Now we can see that it does have a name,
and anonymous function has been replaced with named function.
However, this does create the variable called named function,
which is accessible from the global scope,
so really what this is doing is it's exactly the same as declaring a variable and passing it in.
However, it just does it all in line.
If you're never going to use named function again, it may not be helpful to give it a name
since you're never going to use it again.
But again, you saw how it could be useful in debugging by giving it this name.
In this particular case, it's pretty easy to figure out what's going on
in that type of error debugging because really,
we just called the function immediately from inside callTwice.
But if callTwice had passed that function to another function
and another function and called much later,
it may be very far disconnected from where we actually defined our anonymous function
to where it's actually called because it could be stored into a variable and called much later.
By putting that name on it, if we are still unsure of where that anonymous function came from,
the name can offer us a tool for tracking it down.
One last thing about anonymous functions.
There's a cool little trick that you'll see very often in anonymous functions,
and that's called a self-executing anonymous function.
You remember that functions create their own scope.
And in JavaScript, that's the only way to create a new scope.
In other languages, different structures can create new levels of scope
for either creating new variables that don't leak out to the global scope
or reusing variables by shadowing.
But in JavaScript, the only way you can create a new scope is through a function.
But sometimes it doesn't make sense to really name a function and just call it.
Well, what we can do is if we wanted to create a new scope, we can do exactly that.
Let's create a function and call it immediately.
One way you could do this is we'll say tempFunction,
and then from within here we can create any variable we want--a, b, c--
use them to our heart's content,
and not worry about a, b, and c being visible from the global scope.
This is especially needed in JavaScript because all of the scripts in our page
run in the same global scope.
So if 2 scripts use the same variable,
at the global scope they could interact poorly.
So it's good to scope all your variables.
And then what we could do is just call tempFunction,
and what we would essentially have is the code running on line 67 here
and whatever extra code here that actually uses a, b, and c running immediately,
but it would keep all the variables contained within that scope.
And that's really useful, but it's a lot of code. And I made a mistake there.
That should have been function tempFunction,
or we could have stored an anonymous function into it.
But let's see what we can do with this.
How about instead of naming the function we create it anonymously?
Since we don't have a name, we can't execute it like that,
but what if we could execute it right from here?
If we surround these in parentheses,
parentheses here are not acting as a function call.
Rather, as parentheses would act in a mathematical expression,
parentheses around a value will just evaluate to that value.
So now right here these parentheses evaluate to a function object.
And since we have a function object, we can call it immediately by using parentheses again.
These parentheses are function execution parentheses,
meaning they can take arguments like arg1, arg2,
but these parentheses here are for syntax reasons--these parentheses right here.
So this is saying everything in here evaluates to a function,
and now that we have this function, we can call it immediately.
This will allow us to do anything we want.
So we can say console.log('from anon function')
And let's just say we're going to pass in 1 and 'hello'.
So if we refresh, we see from anonymous function.
I just had a typo there.
So you'll see this in a lot of JavaScript libraries,
and the reason it's useful is because var a, b, and c
we can create all the variables we want, do all of the stuff that we want,
and we don't have to worry about any variables that we declare properly
being leaked to the global scope and being accessible by other code.
So this is just a little pattern that you'll see very often when you want to create a private scope
where you can put all your variables and not have to worry about them interacting
either by other scripts or other libraries using those same variable names.
So now we've learned how to declare and use functions in JavaScript.
Up next, we'll take a look at some practical examples
of how functions are used in common JavaScript operations.
[??] [Treehouse]